<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Dictated thoughts upon the Presbyterians late petitions for compleat and universall power (in divine ordinances) to be conferred upon the presbyters by humane authority.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 29 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81459</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1413</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason 669.f.10[48]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204497</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863986</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863986</idno>
            <idno type="VID">162588</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81459)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 162588)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 246:669f10[48])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Dictated thoughts upon the Presbyterians late petitions for compleat and universall power (in divine ordinances) to be conferred upon the presbyters by humane authority.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.) : ill. (metal cut)  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "14 Aprill: London. 1646".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Presbyterianism --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:162588:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>DICTATED THOVGHTS Vpon the Presbyterians late petitions for compleat and univerſall power (in Divine Ordinances) to be conferred upon the PRESBYTERS by Humane Authority.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Urely if theſe Presbyterians did but know indeed what <hi>the true Religion</hi> is, and did <hi>account</hi> it <hi>the life and crown of all</hi> their <hi>I berties and priviledges</hi> (as they pretend) they would not ſo endeavour to infringe the outward (much leſſe the inward) liberties and priviledges of the profeſſors thereof, as they have done and do. If <hi>the manner of a pure and perfect reformation in all Chriſts ordinances</hi> were not hidden from their eyes, which they pretend to <hi>account the beauty of Religion,</hi> they would never ſeek, thus to compell by civil ſanction, uncivil perſons to divine obedience, but hate the caſting of holy things to dogs, and pearls before ſwine, and not torment thoſe by conſtraint to worſhip God, whoſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is abhorred by God. A mind well informed, knoweth that Gods true worſhip muſt proceed from the mind: The mind muſt be moved by reaſon, not by rigour. To conſtrain men to the poſitive duties of the firſt Table of Gods Law, is not mans, but Gods. It's the devine unction of the word (not the civil ſanction of the world) that frameth men in a ſpirituall poſture pleaſing to God. Thoſe perſons that go this way to work, and whom <hi>God</hi> hath ſo <hi>much honoured</hi> to <hi>promote and accompliſh ſuch a reformation</hi> lay the foundation of the Lords houſe upon the rock, and are to be accounted as thoſe famous witneſſes were <hi>in the days of King Edward, and Queen Elizabeth of happy memory.</hi> Thoſe that do o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, are ſandy foundation-layers, friends to <hi>the midnight of Popery,</hi> and enemies to the <hi>ſweet dawning day of reformation.</hi> What <hi>double honour, divine providence hath devolved upon this age,</hi> by cauſing the light of the truth of Ieſus Chriſt to ſhine in the world <hi>exhibiting</hi> wholſome directions according to the perfect <hi>directory</hi> of the word of God, we deſire to <hi>accept</hi> from the directers <hi>with all thankfulneſſe.</hi> But in this work of ſuch high concernment, all the axes, hammers, and tools of mens inventions, we utterly reject, knowing that ſuch poliſhers are no good reformers, but great poluters of the ſanctuary of the moſt High.</p>
            <p>Spirituall minded men (not perſecuting ſpirits) know that Ieſus Chriſt is the Lord of all adminiſtrations, and that he hath <hi>eſtabliſhed</hi> the <hi>government</hi> and diſcipline of his <hi>Church,</hi> ſufficiently and firmly in his Word, and hath curſed thoſe that add thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, or detract therefrom. To it all perſons muſt yeeld ſubjection, and not dance about the golden calfe of their own invention, much leſſe deſire it to be eſtabliſhed by a <hi>civil ſanction,</hi> for that will not eaſe the extremity of their <hi>perplexed</hi> and <hi>amazed ſpirits,</hi> nor heal the diſtempers of our diſtreſſed Nation. Neither can the Parliament, though <hi>excelling former Parliaments, preſerve Chriſts precious ordinances (and in particular the Lords Supper) from all contempt and profanation</hi> (as theſe Presbyterians ſpeake) for that cannot be in this world: If they do their utmoſt endeavour to keep all ignorant and ſcandalous perſons therefrom, are we to deſire (or doth God require) any more of them in that particular? But ſurely, if it be true as theſe petitioners ſay, that <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Parliaments never had ſuch a learned, pious, and faithfull Synod, to hold forth ſincerely the mind of Chriſt, and the model of Church government agreeable to his will, as this Parliament hath, and yet Church government and diſcipline to this very day doth remain uneſtabliſhed.</hi> Then by this it may appear that the Synod hath been either very negligent, and would not, or deficient, and could not eſtabliſh it, and ſo have not held forth ſincerely the mind of Chriſt agreeable to his will, as is pretended: and theſe Presbyterians themſelves affirm, that their <hi>confeſſion of Faith, &amp; publick Catechiſme, muſt neceſſarily take up a far longer time then can poſſibly be ſpared from ſetling of government, without many unavoydable and deſparate miſchiefs:</hi> And whereas they would have it brought to paſſe by <hi>civil ſanction,</hi> that is Temporall power, to conſtrain all men of and in the Nation, both high and low, rich and poor, bound and free (under pain of corporall puniſhment) to do according to their determinations, in matters of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; And therefore do they in their petition, call out for <hi>a compleat power to be eſtabliſhed upon the Presbyters;</hi> It appeareth they conceive that the government of their Church will not be eſtabliſhed without it, at leaſt in their way, and according to their mind; for without the Temporall ſword, their Kingdom; Power, Glory, Preheminence, and Maintenance, which they ſtand for, fals to the ground. But their preſſing argument is, that <hi>no Parliament ever had ſuch, and ſo many forcible engagements upon them from God, and unto God, as are upon this</hi> And I wiſh the Lord would engage them to him and his more abundantly. And whereas theſe ſay, that <hi>the City of London did never ſo flouriſh with ſuch a conſcionable and painfull ministry, as at this day:</hi> I deſire they were all more conſcionable and painfull in good, and then the City of London would flouriſh indeed But whereas theſe queſtion <hi>whence then ſhould it be that the children being come ſo near to the birth, there is yet no ſtrength to bring forth?</hi> If they mean their two children, <hi>viz.</hi> power and maintenance; it is becauſe the Man child Ieſus Chriſt with his rod of Iron, is about to cruſh the Prieſtly power and maintenance, which they have conceived in their minds, and ſo much cry out for with their mouths.</p>
            <p>But theſe men who will not be content to bear with others in Religion, call out for others to bear with them; ſaying, <hi>Bear with us a little in this fervor of our ſpirits (it is for our Religion, Reformation, and the Houſe of our God, &amp; we cannot hold our peace)</hi> They cannot hold their peace! and why? becauſe they have not temporall power, to ſtop the mouthes of thoſe who ſtand for their Religion, and the Houſe of their God, and cannot hold their peace, more then they; though not in craving for temporall power a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Presbyterians, as the Presbyterians call out for it againſt them. <hi>What way ſoever we caſt our eyes</hi> (ſay they) <hi>we cannot but ſee moſt ſad fruits of the not ſetling of Church government to this day:</hi> Here they ſtill lay their old creeping accuſation, as if Church government were not eſtabliſhed! Surely, If the Angels of the Lord had not ſmitten them with ſpirituall blindnes, they would before this, have found the door of the viſible Church; And if their hearts had not been hardned by the deceitfulnes of ſin, they would ere this have entered into it: for Church government was eſtabliſhed by Ieſus Chriſt, and put in execution by his Saints long ago, though contrary to the minds of the common multitude, and their blind guides; yea, they waited not for the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er or command of civil Magiſtrates, [for Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> and ſuch as ſhee, would never aſſent unto the true Religion] but the Saints did ſet themſelves to do the work which Chriſt had ſent them about, and do remain, through the power of God, unto this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent day, executing the Eccleſiaſticall and Miniſteriall power of the Goſpel, though contrary to the decrees of men. And it is not the want of ſetling Church goverment, which cauſeth ſo many heriſies, which they ſpeak of. Heriſies do ariſe, that thoſe who are approved, may be made manifeſt amongſt us: 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 19 convincing the ſinfull ſects with ſound poſitions, and not with ſatanicall perſecutions, which will neither provoke them to good, nor deter them from evil, peoples perſecuting them with the ſword, and not convincing them by the word, hath hardned their hearts, and made them to bleſſe themſelves in their own ſeducing waies, ſuppoſing them to be the perſecuted waies of God, and all men as they do perceive this Presbyterian way to be a perſecuting way, do endeavour to draw back their ſhoulders, and ſtand a far off, and beware of ſuch an envious monſter, that will ſuffer no man to dwell peaceably by him in the world, unleſſe they be of the ſame Religion with him, yea, by this means ſome precious truths of Chriſt, taught by the Presbyterians, are by ſome (not credited, but) ſuſpected, by otherſome exceedingly contemn'd as falſhood, becauſe handed by perſecuting ſenſuall ſpirits, whereas, if theſe would content themſelves with the gift of God, not tormenting, but ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhing ſuch (by the Scriptures) in the ſpirit of meeknes, without ranker, malice, envie, evil ſpeeches, or rigorous actions, the deceived would be undeceived, Heriticks may be converted, and heriſies ſuppreſſed, though as damnable and dangerous as theſe their poſitions are falſe and ſcandalous: But theſe Presbyterians taking it for granted that Church government is not ſetled to this day; They conclude ſaying, that <hi>hence many abhominable errors, and damnable heriſies are broached amongſt us without controul,</hi> without controul! (ſay they) Hereby it appeareth they would have power from the civil magiſtrate to controul, as if the word were not a ſufficient weapon, but ſuppoſe the blind Presbyters were all made controulers, they had need of good ſpectacles to diſcern who to controul, leaſt they controul truth inſteed of error, and controul their betters, who excell them in wiſdom, piety, and honeſty; Their armes muſt be long and ſtrong, leſt they in controuling of others, are controuled themſelves, and their own weapons fly in their own faces. O old malice! the feeder of faction, and breeder of diviſion, that doſt ſo eye and envie the ſweet unity, harmony, fidelity, and victory of the Engliſh Armies under the command of the Parliament, when wilt thou come to an end? Thy fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers the blood-thirſty Biſhops, and their ſharking ſhavelings, would never be quiet, till they were inſnared (as they are) in the vain works of their own hands, ſurely as they did, ſo doſt thou; and as they are, ſo ſhalt thou be; The precious truths which Ieſus Chriſt hath ſealed with his blood, are trampled under foot by thy children, thy ſervants prophane the pure and holy ordinances of Chriſt. Is there any of theſe presbyters that do not polute, prophane, and trample under foot Chriſts precious truths? are they not their own witneſſes againſt themſelves? who have caſt down the Biſhops, and are ſet in their ſeats, build up ſuperſtitiouſly, what before they puld down; caſt down the Prelates callings as Antichriſtian, yet from them do they derive their ordination, who have it from the Pope of Rome, that ſecond beaſt, mentioned <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. 11. which roſe up out of the earth, having 2. horns like the Lambe, but ſpeaking as the dragon And hence I beleeve the ordinances of Chriſt are wofully profaned by perſons groſly ignorant and ſcandalous, and alſo by perſons of knowledge, that do not walk up to their light: for the Presbyterians have had time enough, and have not yet excomunicated their prophane comunicants, nor ſeparated themſelves from them, but have their children baptized by, and receive the Supper from, ſuch who are ſcandalous in their callings, time-ſerving popelings, wandring ſtars, Antichriſtian Prieſts, who have no calling to the work of the miniſtry, more then Ieroboams prieſts; They ſay <hi>multitudes of unſtable ſoules have fallen off,</hi> But from whence? not from the Church of Chriſt, but from the Church of England, in which they were before unſtable, but not the more for falling off therefrom. And if any one maintain <hi>ſtrange Sects,</hi> (as they ſpeak) It is not the Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates; for they withſtand them all, and particularly the ſect of blaſphemous perſecuting treacherous Presbyterians, and will not pray with them, much leſſe ſuffer them to be incorporated into their ſeparated Aſſemblies, unleſſe they renounce their erronious o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions; and therefore theſe Presbyterians charge the ſeparates falſly: neither do they ſet up <hi>illirerate perſons to be their Paſtors,</hi> but ſuch, that the meaneſt of them is able to confound the greateſt popiſh Presbyter in the world, and that by ſound arguments from Scripture, without carnall weapons. And though <hi>thy manage their meetings with boldnes,</hi> becauſe they are righteous, and confide in thoſe who are called Gods, and children of the moſt High, <hi>(Pſal.</hi> 86. 2.) yet they are far from <hi>inſolency</hi> (as theſe inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Presbyterians lyingly ſpeak) and furtheſt of all from <hi>contempt of all authority:</hi> for they acknowledge authority, knowing it is the ordinance of God, and therefore they will not reſiſt the higher powers, but protect them with their lives and eſtates, as is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant to this day; but the Pope conceiveth that all power is given unto him, and that therefore whoſoever he be, whether magiſtrate or other, that contemns his authority, he contemns all authority, even ſo ſay the Presbyterians, <hi>in contempt of all authority, to the diſturbance of the City, every one doing that which is right in his own eyes, and there is no courſe to reclaim them;</hi> all which accuſations are notorious falſe: for the ſeparates bring not the leaſt diſturbance in the City, but it is Demetrius and his craftſmen, who incite the rude multitude to diſturbe them at their meetings, to the danger of their lives; And if any tranſgreſſe the ſecond table of Gods law, it being made known to the magiſtrate, he hath power immediatly to puniſh him as it is meet according to the law And thoſe that tranſgreſſe the firſt table of Gods law, means is uſed by the miniſters of the Goſpel to reclaim them alſo (by the ſpirituall ſword of Gods word, which is profitable for doctrine, for reproof, for correction, for inſtruction in righteouſnes) 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 16. whether they be none-Churchers, omni Churchers, Anabaptiſts, the ſect of the Libertines, prophane Presbyterians, Heathens, Iewes, Turks, Papiſts, or any ſect under heaven; And if any of all theſe rebell againſt the rules of morality, the magiſtrate (without the miniſter) hath power to puniſh him according to his offence: and the miniſter without the magiſtrate may (and doth) uſe the ſpirituall power which the Lord hath given him, to perſwade the Conſcience; and therefore theſe Presbyterians in ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that <hi>every one doth that which is right in his own eyes, and there is no courſe to reclaim them,</hi> do thereby caſt an aſperſion not only upon the people in generall, but on the magiſtrates and miniſters in ſpeciall. And ſuch fire-brands as theſe Presbyterians, cauſe the <hi>unnaturall ſtames of diviſion (eſpecially about Church government) In the ſame kingdom betwixt people and people, In the ſame City, betwixt miniſter and miniſter, in the ſame congregation, betwixt Paſtor and flock, yea, in the ſame family betwixt master and ſervant, betwixt Parents and children, betwixt husbands and wives:</hi> And it appeareth thus, becauſe when ſome differ from otherſome, and walk up to their light, then do the Presbyters, teach the Presbyterians to perſecute them divers waies, ſeeking to draw them back by carnall compulſion, and the tender conſciences not being willing to be forced, further then the light of reaſon in them: immediatly the fire of contention, proceeding from the Presbyterians ſecred conſciences, breaks forth into a flame, as it is ſpread over Kingdoms, betwixt people and people, in the ſame City one miniſter vilifieth another, in the ſame congregation (or pariſh) the miniſter and the people are at it, yea, in families, the Presbyters ſet the maſter to perſecute the ſervant, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage the ſervant to deſpiſe the maſter, who is not of their mind, hence ariſeth perſecution againſt the children by the father, and againſt the father by their children, yea the husbands are taught by the antichriſtian Presbyters, to lord it over the conſciences of the wives, and wives to perſecute their husbands: inſomuch as when any one declareth himſelf to be a ſeparate, or an independant, immediatly their neereſt Presbyterian friends alienate their affection, becauſe he differs from them in judgement, and break out into many bitter and reproach full contentions, and open perſecutions, no marvell then that <hi>God hath of late manifeſted divers ſad and remarkable tokens of his diſpleaſure againſt England and Scotland, both by ſword and peſtilence,</hi> and deſtroyed many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands, what may the impenitent remnant then expect, who are not killed by theſe plagues, <hi>Rev.</hi> 9. 20. but the cup of the wine of Gods wrath, to be powred out without mixture, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14 10 judgement without mercy, upon them who ſhew no mercy; <hi>Iam.</hi> 2 13. Surely it is laid up in ſtore with God, and ſealed up among his treaſures: To him belongeth vengeance and recompence, their foot ſhall ſlide in due time, for the day of their calamity is at hand, and the things that ſhall come upon them make haſt, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32. 34. 35. And ſurely the diviſions between miniſter and miniſter, paſtor and flock, is not amongſt the ſeparates but rather in the Church of England: neither do the ſeparates <hi>deſpiſe Orthodox miniſters,</hi> nor <hi>diſcourage them in their miniſtry,</hi> nor <hi>diſharten</hi> or <hi>deterre hopefull plants from the miniſtry:</hi> But it is the monopolizing Presbyters, who ſeek to bind all preaching in their own hands, as if none had the ſpirit of God to divide the word aright, but they, and ſuch as are authorized by their patentee-licencers for preaching, even like unto thoſe 4. Angels which John ſaw, ſtanding upon the four corners of the earth, to hold the 4 winds of the earth, that the wind ſhould not blow on the earth, nor on the Sea, nor on any trees, <hi>Rev</hi> 7. 1. Therefore if it were tryed and examined the <hi>Orthodox all miniſters</hi> would prove to be the independant preachers, and not the Presbyterian praters, that think when they have got up in the pulpit, they may crow without controul, And inſteed of godly ruling, fall to ungoſple like railing, at the people of God, to the ſadding of the hearts of their owne hearers, and cauſing the beſt affected amongſt them, to forſake their publike aſſemblies of England, and go where they may be better edified, even amongſt thoſe who are by the Presbyterians pretended to be <hi>teachers of new Goſpel,</hi> but as the Presbyterians do by the ſeparates, ſo the Epicurian Athenians did by Paul, ſome ſaid, what will this babler ſay? otherſome, he ſeemeth to be a ſetter forth of ſtrange Gods,? becauſe he preached unto them Ieſus, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection; <hi>Acts</hi> 17. 18. But <hi>Paul</hi> was not ſo as they would have had him to be, but reproved their ſuperſtition, even ſo the ſeparates are not as the Presbyterians would have men think them to be, they plead not for <hi>the univerſall toleration of all religions and opinions,</hi> but would have all to profeſſe and practize the true Religion (not that any religion is to be perſecuted) but all rebellions proſecuted, neither do they <hi>wilfully contemn the ſabbath, and month-daies of humiliation, backt by the authority of Parliament,</hi> much leſſe do they <hi>open a wide door to all prophaneſſe and licentiouſneſſe,</hi> as theſe Presbyterians maliciouſly ſpeak, if that were true, <hi>the hearts of the truly godly,</hi> would <hi>groan</hi> more then they do, and <hi>our brethren of Scotland</hi> would have more cauſe of <hi>aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> then they have: And as for the <hi>enemies ſcorning and inſulting,</hi> we are not to regard it, but walk ſo in offenſively, that they may be convinced, and acknowledge the Spirit of God in us, and not aſpirit of giddines, which (if theſe ſpeak true) they ſay the Presbyterians are <hi>given up to:</hi> And whereas theſe ſay, thoſe <hi>look at this City as a ſtage of faction and herifie;</hi> that is a ſlander put upon this honourable City (for no better end (as may be well conceived) then to breed a combuſtion amongſt the Citizens, by raſing perſecution againſt honeſt well affected men, under the notion of independants) meerly out of ſpight, to miſchief the City, which hath been ſo active in defence of the Kingdom, againſt thoſe rebels and traytors, and their aſſiſtants, who irriligiouſly ſcorn and inhumanly fight againſt both Church and State, the true Religion, and profeſſors thereof, But herein the proverb is verified, he that walketh uprightly in his way, is an abhomination to the wicked, And yet, though their <hi>distempers</hi> ſhould <hi>grow more incu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable,</hi> and the <hi>reformation</hi> of the generality of the people, every day <hi>more difficult and improbable,</hi> yet no doubt but God will have his number, in ſpight of all malignant oppoſers, the remnant ſhall return to the mighty God of Jacob, and he will ſave them, The conſumation decreed ſhall overflow with righteouſnes, from God to them, which people he hath formed for himſelf, and they ſhall ſhew forth his praiſe, and haſtily, according to their holy Covenant (when the great mountainis become a plain) compleat the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation in all the deſireable perfections of it, not by might, nor by power, but by the Spirit of the Lord.</p>
            <p>Surely if theſe Presbyterians did but ſeriouſly <hi>conſider theſe things</hi> they would (do, what they ſay they <hi>could</hi> do) even <hi>pour out their very ſouls in</hi> them, and be in bitterneſſe for their ſweet Saviour, the crimſon blood of whoſe tender heart, they have ſpilt, by their piercing ſpear of perſecution, and <hi>in this concerning cauſe of God and Religion,</hi> they would joyn peaceably and unanimouſly with the Parliaments cordiall friends, againſt their mortall enemies, and <hi>ſpare neither their prayers, nor tears, nor outward eſtate, nor limbs, nor blood, nor</hi> their <hi>deareſt lives, for</hi> the publick, But endeavour in the way of holynes, <hi>highly to pro<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>rte a ſpeedy and perfect reformation in all matters of Religion, and value it above their worldly comforts, and caſt out fear of all worldly croſſes,</hi> and reſolve rather to ſuffer perſecution, with Gods people, then perſecute them, and behave themſelves meckly, lovingly, and moderately towards all men. Then may they juſtly expect to have the favour and countenance of heaven, and to be accounted by the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inhabitants of TSion, of that coeleſtiall number, whom <hi>God ſhall fully bleſſe with compleat deliverance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore they might do well to <hi>importune</hi> the Parliament, not for perſecution, but for a publick toleration.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>That as</hi> they <hi>tender the happines</hi> of the miſerable members of the Church of England (which theſe term a <hi>miſerable Church) the true proſperity of this afflicted City,</hi> and diſtracted <hi>Kingdom, the timely comfort of all</hi> their <hi>reall friends, the ſeaſonable cure of all</hi> their <hi>deep diſtempers, before they grow remedileſſe, the haſtning of the Kingdoms enlargement from all its preſſing diſtreſſes, its enjoyment of all contrary bleſſings from the Lord, the exaltation of the name of God, whoſe glory is now</hi> by the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Church of England, <hi>prophaned to the duſt,</hi> and their <hi>Faithfull performing of Covenant</hi> and promiſes, they <hi>would make all poſſible haſt</hi> forthwith to ſuppreſſe <hi>by their civil ſanction,</hi> all ſuch perſons, who violently break the bounds of civillity, and morality, by oppreſſing tender conſciences compulſively, againſt the very light and law of nature, and right reaſon, which being done, will be more forcible for bringing a ſpeedy reformation, then a thouſand ſuch Synodian models theſe Presbyterians boaſt of, and ſay the <hi>Synod according to their wiſdom have preſented.</hi> And let them cauſe a confeſſion of Faith [according to the word of God] to be produced forthwith, and <hi>a Catechiſme,</hi> according to it, that ſo ignorant perſons may be rightly informed in their minds, and perſwaded to enter into aright ſpirituall order, which is the readieſt way to eſtabliſh <hi>Church government,</hi> and not ſeek to ſettle <hi>Church government</hi> firſt, and make a beleef and <hi>Catechiſe</hi> afterwards, which diſorderly manner of proceeding, it ſeemes theſe Presbyterians can patiently endure, yea, greedily ſwallow down, approve of, and juſtifie. But away with all tenets that make way for this popiſh maxime, that men muſt beleeve as the Church beleeves, ſurely they are happy who are far enough from ſuch a Church, that cannot ſpare time to produce a confeſſion of Faith, leſt unavoydable and deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate miſchiefs ſhould (as theſe ſay) come unto them Ye Presbyterians, take heed what ye do, enter not into the fellowſhip, before you are in the faith, leſt your latter end be worſe then your beginning, examine, try and prove your ſelves, come not into the holy aſſembly, ſit not down in the Lords Sanctuary, without the wedding garment, leaſt the wrath of God fiercely ſieze upon your poor ſoules, and make you as miſerable in puniſhment, as you are in ſin, and bind you hand and foot, and caſt you into the dark dungeon of everlaſting perdition, to be tormented evermore in the preſence of the holy Angels, and in the preſence of the Lamb, where the victory of the Saints, ſhall not be the glory of ſinners. Then that harlot Tyre ſhall ſing no more melodious ſongs of remembrance, but ſhall be utterly forgotten. And all the ſermons of her falſe prophets (which preach for hire) ſhall be as ſentences of condemnation unto them, when the mountains and hills of magiſteriall power and authority ſhall not be able to hide or cover them from the wrath of the Lamb.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Theſe Presbyterians ſhould not have petitioned unto men for <hi>power</hi> and authority, to confer upon the Presbyters, that which is only in the power of God. Divine right muſt be ſought for only from God, Humane power from men in authority. The greateſt men on earth can give no more then what themſelves have; but theſe would have the Parliament to give them ſuch a compleat meaſure of power and authority, as may fully enable the Presbyters to maintain all Chriſts ſacred ordinances, in their higheſt ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor and purity, held forth in the word, &amp;c. This is Gods gift, and none other,—and he will give it to his Church and Presbytery, and to none elſe in the world. Its an inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance which cannot be purchaſed by the temporall ſword, all the carnall weapons in the world will not procure it: for the Lord will fight againſt ſuch fighters, who inſteed of a holy and glorious reformation, bring a ſinfull and ſhamefull defamation, adding to theſe diſtractions, more deſtructions, and ruinations, in whoſe ſecrets, let not the ſouls of the Saints enter, their glory let them not unite unto them in their impure, imperfect, and impious waies: for though the path of the juſt, is as the ſhining light, which ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth more and more unto the perfect day, yet the way of the wicked is as darknes, they know not at what they ſtumble. <hi>Prov.</hi> 4. 18. 19.</p>
            <p>O that the Lord would open the eies of theſe Presbyterians, that they may ſee their ſinne, and turn unto him, and behold that holy mount Zion, which the Lord will more and more eſtabliſh upon the top of the mountaines, and exalt above the hilles, that they may diſcerne the light of God, and walk uprightly therein, then they may with holy reſolution ſay, that though they repent of their former ſinne, yet they ſhall not repine at their future doings, or ſufferings, in reference to the poſeſſion and practice of the glorious truths of God, But expect conſtancy from God to continue triumphing in his praiſe, for crowning his ſpouſe with ſpirituall glory, and for lifting up the hearts of his Saints in theſe ſacred things to do worthily.</p>
            <figure/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
